there are many factors that contribute
to cardiovascular disease but among the
most impactful is elevated blood
pressure fortunately it's also one of
the factors that we can change the most
dramatically in fact even small changes
can offer outsized benefits in
protecting against things like your
brain blowing open or by Prim terms
suffering a stroke or your heart saying
nah I've had enough or in Prim terms
suffering a heart attack we also know
that exercise is one of the major
players in reducing blood pressure but
believe it or not the crown for the best
blood pressure reducing ability is held
by a weird type of exercise so let's
discuss the data there are several types
of exercise from general terms like I
resistance training and endurance
training to more specific descriptions
like biking running push-ups lifting
some iron crushing some skulls and maybe
I took that last one a bit too far the
point being there are different types of
exercise yet only one rain supreme ruler
of the Galaxy but instead of me yapping
on about it I had the distinct honor of
having a lovely conversation with Gil
from nutrition Made Simple on this very
topic Dr Gil carvalo has his medical
doctorate and his PhD and describes this
really well so let's listen in and then
we'll will come back with the data from
two metaanalyses including up to
270 studies Yes you heard that right
270 studies and there's studies looking
at the best exercises to lower to lower
blood pressure which a lot of people
struggle with and they they looked at
everything they looked at Cardio they
looked at lifting weights they' looked
at running cycling like all of this list
and isometric was at the very top okay
so isometric exercise we'll return back
to Gil on a protocol for how to use
isometric exercise to lower blood
pressure but for the time being let's
crack open some of these analyses to get
a clearer picture of what Gil is talking
about if we lean on this analysis the
researchers pulled 270 studies and
Quantified the blood pressure effect of
a bunch of different exercise types then
because this is what's known as a
network metaanalysis the researchers are
able to compare
the magnitude of the effect I.E how much
blood pressure was lowered through
indirect comparisons of many exercise
types they actually show that in what's
known as a beian ranking panel we have
different exercise types abbreviated on
the right side there the higher up into
the green that it goes the better the
probability that the treatment is the
most effective you can see that the
control is at the very bottom that's
usually the no exercise condition then
at the very top you can see I that
stands for isometric exercise training
exactly what Gil was talking about then
Gil says something else that's really
astounding they saw a reduction of 10
points 10 millimeters Mercury with the
program of isometric exercises which is
in the same range as you often get with
blood pressure loading meds it's kind of
an amazing result a 10o drop in blood
pressure that's a huge drop especially
as we'll get into how easy this is if we
pop open that same analysis as before
and we look at a forest plot of the data
this is a shortened for ease of
understanding we can see isometric
exercise training up top here then the
researchers have broken it up by three
different versions of isometric training
isometric hand grip leg extension and
wall squat the red diamond and the black
dots correspond to the average result of
all the studies combined in this case 24
studies that uh thick black line
indicates no blood pressure lowering
effect so if the diamonds and the dots
fall to the right that indicates a blood
pressure lowering effect we can see that
in total isometric exercises reduce
systolic blood pressure that's the top
number on your blood pressure readings
by about eight points however something
like wall squats is estimated to reduce
blood blood pressure by around 10 points
pretty remarkable and confirmed in this
analysis as well but how do we use this
information what kind of protocol could
we follow while we'll dive into that
next if you're interested too I wrote a
detailed research review going into some
more of the nuances and other exercises
if you're a physionic Insider you have
access to it including The Insider
podcast a full library of videos and
articles with applicable takeway ways
and much more it's linked in the
description if you're so inclined but
let's discuss how to implement isometric
exercise it's really simple which is why
the blood pressure effect is
additionally amazing so just to give one
quick example of a what a program could
look like doing a wall squat for a
minute or two uh if you can hold it if
not you start shorter and then as your
resistance as your capacity increases
you increase the the length basically a
minute or two of a wall squat then rest
for a couple minutes do four sets of
that two or two or three times a week
that's literally like a few minutes uh
of your day and it can have these these
kind of amazing results and certainly at
the level of blood pressure yep pretty
simple doing a wall squat looks like
this you hold a 90° seated position
against a wall for 1 to 2 minutes
work up to it if you can't do that and
you do that for three to five times per
session you would also perform two to
five sessions per week the greatest bang
for your buck H would probably be in
that two to three times per week range
that's literally it but Gil also said
this which I found pretty funny so
there's a couple things like that and
the the beauty of that is they're pretty
quick they are free of charge you don't
need to go to some fancy gym to do you
can do it in your home you can do it
anywhere you can do it at work and you
have a break you go outside you lean
against the building and you squat uh it
might look ridiculous to to passers by
but you can do it anywhere you can do to
the bathroom the great sitting
Revolution people randomly rising up
from their desks going outside lining
the walls of buildings in a static squat
position thousands of them lowering
their blood pressure in the bushes
against light poles against Park cars
against each other back to back it's a
funny mental image anyway check out
Gil's Channel where we discuss more
health tips in a video of his it'll be
linked in the description or if you're
interested in more on the power of
exercise and heart health check out this
next video it discusses reversing your
heart's age
oh